Welcome! Today we'll explore QuickSort, one
of the most efficient sorting algorithms.
QuickSort uses a divide and conquer strategy. It picks
a pivot element and partitions the array around it.
Let's visualize QuickSort with an example array containing the
numbers 6, 3, 8, 1, 9, 4, and 2.
First, we select the last element, 2, as
our pivot. We'll highlight it in red.
Now we partition the array. Elements smaller than the pivot go
to the left, and larger elements go to the right.
The pivot is now in its correct position. We recursively
apply the same process to the left and right sub-arrays.
After recursively sorting all partitions, we get the final sorted
array: 1, 2, 3, 4, 6, 8, and 9.
Let's examine QuickSort's time complexity. In the average case,
it operates in O of n log n time.
However, in the worst case, when the pivot is always the
smallest or largest element, it degrades to O of n squared.
The best case also achieves O of n log n when partitions are balanced.
QuickSort is widely used due to its efficiency
and in-place sorting capability. Thank you for watching!