Welcome to this comprehensive 5-minute guide on the Selection Sort algorithm.
Sorting is a fundamental operation in computer science, used everywhere from
organizing lists to optimizing databases. Selection Sort is one of the
simplest algorithms to understand and implement. It works by repeatedly finding
the minimum element from the unsorted part of the array and
placing it at the beginning of the sorted part. Over the
next sections, we'll cover its motivation, pseudocode, step-by-step examples, complexity analysis,
comparisons, and real-world applications. By the end, you'll have a deep
understanding of how it works visually and why it's useful for
small datasets.
Before diving in, let's recall what sorting means. Given an
unsorted list like [5, 2, 8, 1, 9], sorting rearranges
it into non-decreasing order: [1, 2, 5, 8, 9]. Selection
Sort does this efficiently for beginners by selecting the smallest
remaining element each time. It's not the fastest for large
data, but its simplicity makes it perfect for learning.
Selection Sort was invented in the early days of computing when
efficiency wasn't always paramount, but simplicity was. It's motivated by the
human way of sorting cards: you pick the smallest card and
place it first, then the next smallest, and so on. This
in-place sorting requires no extra memory, unlike Merge Sort. It's ideal
for educational purposes and small arrays where O(n^2) time is acceptable,
say up to 100 elements. Historically, it appears in Donald Knuth's
'The Art of Computer Programming' as a baseline algorithm.
Compared to random selection, Selection Sort guarantees progress by
fixing one element per pass. It's stable in some
implementations but not inherently. We'll see why it's preferred
over Bubble Sort—no unnecessary swaps after finding the min.
The basic idea is straightforward: Divide the array into two parts—sorted
(left) and unsorted (right). Initially, the sorted part is empty. In
each iteration, scan the unsorted part to find the index of
the minimum element, then swap it with the first unsorted element.
This grows the sorted prefix by one each time. For an
array of n elements, you do n-1 passes.
Visualize it: Start with full unsorted. After first pass, smallest is
at position 0. Second pass: next smallest at 1, and so
on. No backtracking—each pass is independent and linear scan.
Here's the pseudocode in detail. We use a for loop from
0 to n-2. For each i, assume i is the minimum
index initially. Then nested loop from i+1 to n-1 to find
any smaller element. If found, update min_index. After inner loop, swap
arr[i] with arr[min_index]. This ensures the i-th position is correctly filled.
Notice the nested loops: outer for positions, inner for
scanning minimums. Swaps happen only once per outer iteration,
unlike Bubble Sort's many swaps. This makes it efficient
in terms of swaps: exactly n-1 swaps worst-case.
Let's trace a small array: [3, 1, 4, 1, 5]. Pass 1
(i=0): scan 1,4,1,5. Min is 1 at index 1. Swap 3 and
1: [1, 3, 4, 1, 5]. Now position 0 fixed.
Pass 2 (i=1): scan from 4,1,5. Min=1 at index 3. Swap 3 and 1:
[1, 1, 4, 3, 5]. Pass 3 (i=2): scan 3,5. Min=3 at 3. Swap
4 and 3: [1, 1, 3, 4, 5]. Pass 4: 5 is min. Done.
For deeper visualization, consider [64, 25, 12, 22, 11].
Pass 1: Highlight scanning (yellow), find min 11 (red),
swap with 64. Array becomes [11, 25, 12, 22,
64]. The sorted part is marked green, unsorted orange.
Pass 2: Sorted [11 | 25,12,22,64]. Scan unsorted, min=12 at
index 2. Swap with 25: [11,12,25,22,64]. Notice how the green
sorted region grows. This visual separation helps track progress.
Continue similarly: Each pass reduces unsorted size
by 1. No overlaps in logic—pure selection.
Now a 10-element array: [7,2,9,5,1,6,10,3,8,4]. Pass 1 finds 1
(index 4), swaps to front. It would take 9
passes total, each scanning decreasing lengths: 10,9,...,2 comparisons.
Visualizing all passes: Watch mins bubble to front. Total swaps: 9.
This shows scalability issues for large n, but clarity for small.
Time complexity: Outer loop n-1 times, inner loop averages n/2
comparisons. Exact: sum from 1 to n-1 = n(n-1)/2 comparisons,
plus n-1 swaps. Thus O(n^2) time, quadratic growth.
Graph shows quadratic curve. For n=10,
~45 ops; n=100, 5000 ops—slows dramatically.
Space: O(1) extra—only min_idx variable. In-place swaps modify array
directly. Not stable: equal elements may swap, changing order.
Not adaptive: always full scans even if sorted.
Stability example: [2a, 1, 2b]. Sorts to [1, 2a, 2b]
but may swap 2a and 2b if positions dictate.
Properties: Exactly n-1 swaps. Prefers small arrays. Online? No, needs full
scan. Can be optimized by skipping if arr[i] <= arr[min_idx].
Vs Bubble: Selection does one swap per pass, Bubble many.
Both O(n^2), but Selection fewer writes. Vs Insertion: Insertion adaptive
(O(n) best), shifts elements; Selection always scans fully.
Applications: Embedded systems, small datasets, teaching. Not for big
data—use QuickSort/ TimSort. In Python, use sorted() instead.
Summary: Selection Sort selects mins sequentially, O(n^2) time,
O(1) space. Visual, simple, foundational. Thanks for watching!