Welcome to this comprehensive explanation of the Heap Sort algorithm.
Heap Sort is a powerful comparison-based sorting algorithm that leverages
the heap data structure to achieve efficient sorting in O(n
log n) time complexity. Unlike quicksort, which can degrade to
O(n squared) in worst cases, Heap Sort guarantees optimal performance
regardless of input. Over the next several minutes, we'll dive
deep into heaps, how to build them, the key heapify
operations, the full algorithm, a detailed step-by-step example, complexity analysis,
and real-world applications. By the end, you'll fully understand how
to implement and visualize Heap Sort.
Sorting algorithms are fundamental in computer science, used everywhere from
databases to search engines. Heap Sort stands out because it
first transforms the array into a heap—a special tree structure—then
repeatedly extracts the maximum element to build the sorted array.
This in-place sorting makes it memory efficient too. Let's start
by understanding what a heap is.
A heap is a complete binary tree that satisfies the heap
property. It's 'complete' meaning all levels are fully filled except possibly
the last, which is filled left to right. We represent it
compactly in an array where for a node at index i,
its left child is at 2i+1 and right at 2i+2—assuming 0-based
indexing. This array representation avoids pointers, saving space. Heaps are crucial
for priority queues and sorting.
Visually, the tree mirrors the array: root at index
0, children derived by doubling indices. This duality allows
efficient operations. Next, we'll explore the two types: max
heaps and min heaps, defined by their ordering property.
A max heap ensures every parent node is greater than or
equal to its children. This 'max heap property' bubbles the largest
element to the root. In our array view, for every i,
array[i] >= array[2i+1] and array[i] >= array[2i+2]. This property is violated
during insertions or deletions, requiring heapify to restore it.
Here's a valid max heap: [16, 14, 10, 8, 7, 9, 3, 2, 4,
1]. Notice 16 at root, largest. 14 > 8 and 7, 10 > 9
and 3, and so on. The tree view highlights the parent-child inequalities with arrows.
Conversely, a min heap has every parent smaller than or equal
to its children. Ideal for extracting minimums, like Dijkstra's algorithm. Property:
A[i] <= A[2i+1] and A[i] <= A[2i+2]. Heap Sort typically uses
max heaps to sort in ascending order by extracting max repeatedly.
Example min heap: [1, 2, 3, 4, 7, 9, 10, 14, 8,
16]. 1 is smallest at root. Children of 2 are 4 and
7, both larger. This structure supports efficient minimum priority queues.
To sort, we first build a max heap from the unsorted array.
The naive way—insert one by one—is O(n log n), but we can
do better with bottom-up heapify in O(n). Start from the last non-leaf
node (floor(n/2)-1) and call heapify-down on each, propagating properties upward.
Consider unsorted array [4,1,3,2,16,9,10,14,8,7]. Last non-leaf is index 4 (value
9). Heapify-down on 4 swaps 9 with larger child if
needed, then recurse. Repeat backward to root. This linear time
build is a key insight by Floyd.
Heapify-down restores max heap property at a subtree rooted at
index i. Compare A[i] with its largest child. If parent
smaller, swap with largest child and recurse on that child
until property holds. Leaves no recursion. Pseudocode: find largest among
i, left, right; if not i, swap and heapify(largest).
Animation: suppose at i=1, A=[16,4,10,...], children 8 and 7. 10 largest
child, but if 4<10, swap 4 and 10, then check 10's
subtree. Bubbles down violations efficiently, O(log n) worst case.
Heapify-up is used after insertion: start from new leaf, swap
with smaller parent if larger, until root or property holds.
Symmetric to down, used in building bottom-up or inserts. While
parent exists and child > parent, swap.
Example: insert 20 into heap. Append to array end, heapify-up: compare
with parent, swap if larger, bubbling up. O(log n) height.
Heap Sort: 1. Build max heap from array (O(n)). 2. For i from
n-1 to 1: swap root A[0] with A[i], reduce heap size by 1,
heapify-down on root. Largest goes to end, repeat. In-place, stable performance.
Visually, after build, largest at root. Swap to
end, heapify restores subtree, next largest to root,
repeat. Unsorted suffix grows, prefix shrinks.
Let's trace Heap Sort on [4,1,3,2,16,9,10,14,8,7]. First, build max
heap. Start heapify-down from i=4 (9). Children 14 and
8, 14>9>8, swap 9 and 14: now [4,1,3,2,14,9,10,9,8,7]. Then
heapify on 4 (now 9), no children larger.
Next i=3 (2), children 8,7; 8>2, swap 2-8:
[4,1,3,8,14,9,10,9,2,7]. Heapify on 8 (now2), leaf ok. Continue
similarly until full max heap: [16,14,10,8,7,9,3,2,4,1].
Now sorting phase. Heap size=10, swap root 16 with end
1: [1,14,10,8,7,9,3,2,4,16], size=9, heapify-down on 1. Largest child 14 or
10, swap with 14: [14,1,10,8,7,9,3,2,4,16], then on 1 (now1), leaf.
Repeat: swap 14 with 4: [4,10,1,8,7,9,3,2,14,16], heapify yields
next max at root, continue until [1,2,3,4,7,8,9,10,14,16] sorted!
Each extract O(log n), total O(n log n).
Time complexity: Build heap O(n), since heapify-down heights sum to O(n).
Each of n extracts: swap O(1) + heapify O(log n), total
O(n log n). Space O(1) in-place. Worst/average/best all O(n log n),
beats merge sort space-wise, stable unlike quicksort worst-case.
Proof sketch: Height h=log n, nodes at height k
contribute O(n / 2^k * k) work, telescopes to
O(n). Reliable performance makes it great for embedded systems.
Compared to Quicksort: Heap Sort slower constant but guaranteed
O(n log n), no pivot issues. Vs Merge Sort:
in-place, no extra space. Vs Heapsort strengths: priority queues,
median finding, graph algos like Prim/Dijkstra use heap variants.
Applications: OS task scheduling (priority), Huffman coding, k-largest elements.
Python's heapq module uses min-heap for these. Versatile!
To recap: Heap Sort builds a max heap in O(n),
then extracts max n times in O(n log n) total.
Key ops: heapify-up/down maintain properties. Reliable, in-place, O(n log n).
Implement by transforming arrays to trees visually in mind. Thanks
for watching this deep dive—practice with code to master it!