Welcome! Today we will explore the Bubble Sort algorithm,
one of the simplest sorting algorithms in computer science.
Bubble Sort works by repeatedly stepping through the list, comparing adjacent
elements, and swapping them if they are in the wrong order.
Let's visualize this with an example. Here
we have an unsorted array of numbers.
We start by comparing the first two elements. Five
is greater than two, so we swap them.
Now we compare five and eight. They are
already in order, so no swap is needed.
Next, eight and one. Eight is larger, so we swap them.
Finally, eight and nine are in order. The
largest element has bubbled to the end.
We repeat this process, each time the next
largest element bubbles to its correct position.
Now let's analyze the time complexity. Bubble sort has a
worst-case and average time complexity of O of n squared.
However, in the best case, when the array is
already sorted, it only takes O of n time.
The space complexity is O of 1, as it
only requires a constant amount of additional memory.
In conclusion, while Bubble Sort is simple to understand and implement,
it is not efficient for large datasets. Thank you for watching!